[Western music]
[Peter] Good morning guys.
Here the southeastern corner of Arizona.
Outside of the town of Morenci
off there in the distance.
Now Morenci is one of the last few
true company towns in America.
Meaning the company
owns all of the real estate.
Everyone works for the company
either directly or indirectly.
And it's just far removed from the state.
From the rest of the country.
And is the biggest
copper operation in North America.
So today we're going to get out there
on the streets of Morenci.
Talk to the locals and try to get
a better understanding of what it's like
to live in a modern day company town.
Let's do this.
[country music]
Here we are guys, Morenci.
Morenci Motel.
We have the grocery store.
Health center.
And then mine right in the distance there.
So roughly 2000 people
living here currently.
And the mine, from my research is thriving.
Copper prices are up.
A lot is getting extracted out of here.
We're going to get up there today.
I think there's actually
a sweet place to see into the pit.
I think there is.
You know, those are all company homes.
Nobody owns up here. Everybody is renting.
To get somebody that works here in the mine
on camera at a higher level,
impossible from my understanding.
And so I had a guy set up.
He was so excited
to show me around Morenci,
get us in one of the homes here, talk at
a deeper level about company town living.
And his superior said,
"Nope, can't do that."
So that's why it's me solo mission.
Well, we'll get a good understanding
today though guys. I feel it here.
-How are you doing?
-Good. How are you?
[Peter] Good. You've lived here 13 years?
-Yes.
-How is it?
It's pretty good.
It was kind of a shock at first.
We moved here from Show Low
up in the forest, you know,
but there's a lot of good people here.
We've made a lot of friends.
-What's the company town feel if
you've lived outside of the company town?
Now you live in it. What's that like?
It's weird. It's different.
-How so?
I feel like they're more privileged here
just because you work for the company,
you know?
Okay. So no unemployment in town, right?
Not really. No.
It's good though. The company
really takes good care of everybody.
-Pays pretty good here?
-Mm-hmm. Yeah.
When we first moved here,
it was just an empty Dairy Queen building
and the swimming pool.
And they built this fitness center here.
It was kind of crazy because
it doesn't even feel like it belongs here.
It's so huge. It's super nice.
-Health care?
-Yes.
-Full family. Dental?
Dental, vision, yeah. All of it.
-Everything?
Yeah. I mean, he takes a portion
out of the check, but…
-What's your rent?
-Our rent right now is three…
-It's like $360 or something like that.
-$360?
Something like that.
-For a house? For one of these places?
-Yeah. Three bedroom.
Ours is just right down there.
It's a three-bedroom.
I mean, they're old, but…
-You're paying like 1986 prices?
-Mm-hmm.
Very blessed here, I feel like.
-Thank you, guys.
-It's nice meeting you.
-You too.
-Have a good day.
So I was in Bagdad, guys.
Bagdad's another one of
these company towns.
And then people told me, "Hey,
you got to check out Morenci. It's bigger."
It's a bigger mine. It's a bigger town.
And I've just taken a fascination
with the concept of it,
because it's an old concept.
It's been around
in the United States forever.
And at one time,
there were thousands of company towns.
And in those times, it wasn't like this.
I mean, the air quality,
just the way the mines were run,
the way the workers were treated.
Different universe compared to now,
where they're setting up
nice gyms and whatnot.
Look at that baseball field there.
And then, like the lady said,
this was a Dairy Queen
and they've gone all in in it looks like.
Morenci Club,
library, movie theater, Starbucks,
and the gym.
Community center.
So first impressions, guys.
Morenci, very quiet.
Now it is 1030 on a Saturday.
I didn't know what day
would be best.
I thought Monday through Friday,
maybe everyone's working in the mines.
Weekends, they might have more time,
but then
it might be one of those
the mines never stop.
So everyone's on a shift.
So it really doesn't matter.
[Peter] Community center
for the whole town.
For the whole town of Morenci.
So people working in the mine?
Working in the mine
or non-Freeport employees.
Anybody can use our facility.
Big pool setup.
Yeah, we've got an indoor pool
and an outdoor pool.
Ah, that's great.
-Can I walk in? Is that cool?
-Sure.
-What's your name?
-My name is Sandra.
-Sandra. Peter.
-Nice to meet you, Peter.
How long have you been here?
I've been with the company 21 years,
but in this facility 10.
-How's it been?
Fabulous. I love it.
Okay, so they have
a volleyball set up here.
So I've been to West Virginia,
Kentucky.
I think you guys have probably seen
some of those videos. Some of you have.
The old mining towns.
And when that mine runs out,
well, everyone leaves and it's just decay.
And this is the opposite, right?
This is the mine
that is thriving currently.
And from what I read, there's decades
of copper to be had in that mine.
[weights clank]
[weights bang and clank]
-So you live out here?
-Yeah.
-Working the mine?
How is it? It's cool. I like it. Day off,
you come here, you do some exercise.
Where are you from originally?
I'm from Ghana.
-No way!
-Yeah.
How'd you find this place?
Okay, so I moved into Nevada.
Then I found this one online.
-You found it online?
-Yeah.
How is it living in company town?
It's a small town, chill.
Like, low violence.
And I like all the peace.
-Low violence. Like, no crime here?
No crime, so I like it chill.
Come to work out,
goes to the gym, then go to sleep.
-Good pay?
-Yeah. I like it, yeah.
-Company picnic, huh?
-You guys have a company picnic?
-Yeah, Freeport does.
-Freeport does, yeah.
So there are a lot of events going on?
Yeah, this whole parking lot is full.
And the gym and everything, there's just…
Not just from here, they come from Safford,
they come from Lordsburg.
These people attract a lot of people
working at the mine.
-What's the average wage right now?
What would you say?
Average wage?
I don't know, let's say about 80?
-$80,000?
-75, 80.
-Okay. And then rent as we…
-Without overtime.
Without overtime.
Okay, so if you're working overtime,
you can get over $100,000 here?
-Easy, huh?
-Easy.
And then your expenses are like nothing?
Housing is like $600, I think.
I found last night on their website,
$500 for a four bed, two bath house.
Oh, really?
And if you work for the company,
and you don't live in housing,
you get a $700 a month incentive.
They'll give you $700 a month
if you're renting somewhere else.
So all your… I mean, this is super cheap.
I think I pay $35.
-For a family?
Free daycare. For the gym, two hours here.
-Oh, that's cool.
[Peter] Big man, what's going on?
That's you, big man.
Oh, um, nut'n really.
You know, just a working' town.
Workin' town?
You're gonna get your working' on, right?
As in workout?
-Pump some iron?
-Yes, sir. Try to.
-You guys say sir and ma'am out here, huh?
Yes, sir.
-How's the school?
Straight A's across the board here?
-Trying.
-A's and B's.
A's and B's, yeah.
-No C's?
-No C's.
-You telling the truth?
-Yes, sir.
One C, one C.
One C. I like it. Okay.
That's all right.
You'll do well in life no matter what.
If you're fired up and you work hard
and you love what you do.
-See ya.
-You too.
Okay, so the company
that runs this is Freeport-McMoRan
And in Arizona,
copper is a massive part of the economy.
From what I gathered online,
the best thing I could come up with,
roughly 50,000 jobs
are tied in to the copper industry.
And so these kids
down at the parking lot there said
we can just sort of drive
right through the mine,
which is awesome because it's really hard
to get this access sometimes.
I think it's all about do your work,
make your good money,
have your stability,
raise your kids, low expenses.
So they're just pulling,
from my understanding,
this is the rock out of the mountain.
Then somehow they get
the copper out of that.
So very rough estimates.
This mine produces
a billion pounds annually of copper.
There we go. Tunnel time.
Through the mountain.
[Western music]
This just keeps going and going.
Oh wow. Look at this.
Oh my God.
So it's one of the largest
open pit mines in the world.
We've been driving for a while
up and down.
You can see how the road has a fence line
the whole way with barbed wire.
So there's nowhere to really
pull over and get a shot
except this one area.
[machinery whirring]
-[Peter] So you work here.
-[man] I do.
-So that comes out of the mountain, right?
-Yes.
And then there's copper in there?
-There is copper.
-And what do they do? Break it down?
It depends.
Like sometimes it goes to the crushers
and that goes through the whole process
to make copper out of it.
And sometimes they put it in these dumps
and they leach it and then
they collect those in those ponds.
-Oh, those ponds down there?
-Yes.
-So they leach it?
-Put a chemical on it or something?
-Yes.
It's some sort of chemical that basically
gets the copper out of the rock
and then they send it to downstream
processing to make copper out of it.
-Do you know where all this copper goes?
-They have different facilities.
It depends on what the process is.
But eventually, it either
comes back as copper cathode,
which is those copper plates,
or it's hauled to, I believe, Miami,
and that's where they…
-Miami, Arizona?
-Yes.
Not Florida, yes.
-Okay, then it gets shipped out.
-And then it gets shipped out, yes.
-Okay.
I work right across…
Like, if you look from the other side,
there's a small office.
That's the short-range planning office.
-Okay.
-So I work from there, yes.
Okay, are these dump trucks
automated now?
No, they're not. They're still manned.
They're going to automate soon,
though, I think.
At some point, I believe
that's where the industry is going.
-How long you been out here?
With the company, four years.
Where are you from?
I'm originally from Brazil.
The town kind of revolves around mine.
And also the schedules that people work.
So it's definitely more slow-paced.
So how is it?
What's it like down in that world?
Ah, it's a…
Let's just say that
you feel very small, right?
-You feel small, yeah.
It's a massive operation.
It is the largest
open copper mine in North America.
The highway has moved multiple times.
-Oh, they moved the highway?
-Multiple times.
Gotcha.
Don't quote me on that,
but it's called the Million Dollar Highway.
Because it is so expensive.
-Okay, I bet way more than a million
these days, right? That makes sense.
-So they're constantly…
-Any time the mine progresses,
then they have to shift the highway around.
-And ecologically, I mean,
it's tough to say what's going on exactly,
but better than old times, I'm sure.
Yeah, I know that the company
is certified in different, like, standards.
Like, I guess they have
the copper mark who just says that
it is a sustainable operation and all that.
-Okay.
All right, guys.
A lot of information here from Freeport.
We got a Caterpillar tire over here.
So you can see the size, which is…
Well, I'm coming up
a little over halfway on this thing.
So that's what's moving down below there.
Tire weighs 8,625 pounds.
And there is environmental impact for sure.
I'm sure some of you are concerned
about that and I totally get that.
I can't speak as an expert
on that front with these things.
I can say that compared to many years ago,
mining operations,
have gotten much cleaner.
There's also a trade-off, right?
If you want electricity,
you need copper.
If you want an electric car,
you need a lot of copper.
There's no way around that.
Funny story, last night I was in
Silver City, New Mexico,
talking to this guy.
Nice older guy.
And I told him I was going to Morenci.
And he's like, yeah, copper's…
I don't like copper.
I'm like, what do you mean
you don't like copper?
Well, back in the 1930s,
they segregated everyone.
You know, the Latinos and the Whites,
they segregated them.
And I said, yeah, that's not good.
Thank God we're not in the 1930s anymore.
That's no longer a thing.
I went into a mining town recently,
which was Bagdad.
A few videos back, guys.
Went in with an open mind,
just wanting to see what
life was like there, how people liked it.
And from my experience, it was positive.
Most people enjoyed living out there.
That's what they told me.
Sure, some people don't,
but that was the information I came across.
And if it was the opposite,
as in people didn't like living out there,
I would have kept that in the video.
I just wanted to learn what it was like
to live in a company town,
a modern day company town.
And I said, yeah,
it was actually most people liked it.
He wasn't having it.
He didn't like that copper existed.
And we talked for a while longer
and on other things.
And he walked across the street
and got in his Toyota Prius,
and sped off.
I found that sort of interesting.
I think a lot of people are
disconnected from the things
they use on a regular basis.
And copper is something
we all use every single day.
And here's where it comes from.
And that Brazilian guy up there
and these people down here
are the people making it happen.
So we can have
our modern
lifestyles that we all enjoy.
[dump trucks whirring]
See that little dump truck up there?
That's how big it is.
You can hear the blasting.
You just gotta follow those roads down.
See if you can with your eyes there.
See it just winds down the mountain.
It's so wild.
Over a hundred years,
one dump truck load at a time,
They've gotten much bigger
since the old days.
One dump truck load at a time
removed this whole mountain
all the way back there
and stuff we can't even see.
Camera's not even doing it justice.
I know that.
But you can get a sliver here.
I strongly recommend
traveling over here, you guys.
If you're on a road trip,
this is interesting.
It's 360. That's the thing.
The camera's not showing 360.
But it's all around us right now.
So there's that town we came through
right next to Morenci.
Just a couple miles away
that looked very interesting.
Let's go check that place out.
Try to talk to some
locals down there.
Then get a little more
of a tour of Morenci.
[Western music]
[Peter] How you doing?
-[Peter] This is beautiful.
-[woman] Yeah.
-You ladies from here?
-Yeah, I was born and raised here.
-No way. Can I ask you some questions?
-Yeah.
-Okay,
what was that like growing up here?
-Awesome.
-It was pretty cool.
It's a mining town so…
You didn't have to worry about
all the strangers that are here now.
-There's a lot of new people.
-Let kids run around.
-Okay, so it's changed a little.
-Yeah.
-Quite a bit. Not a little.
Yeah, 'cause there's so many
people all over the world
that have came to work here now.
Okay,
so there's people coming and going.
-Yep. Constantly.
-Gotcha.
So back in the day, people lived
in the town, mined in the town, never left?
Yes.
-I was just in Baghdad, Arizona.
It's another Freeport town.
Oh, that's far from here.
-It's far.
-It's like nine hours, isn't it?
-Probably.
-Yeah.
It's far, but the locals there
were telling me it's like that now.
You let your kids go out,
it's totally safe and cool.
But you're saying it's not like that here?
Yeah, it's like that here.
Not really. I don't think so.
-No? Okay.
There's too many people coming and going.
There's not enough housing.
-So you've got people sleeping at Circle K.
-There's a lot of drugs here.
-Oh, really?
-Yeah.
Is Morenci the same, or that's here?
Mostly just here in Clifton,
it's more drugs here.
-This is not a company town?
-No, never has been.
-Okay. Okay.
-Never has been? Oh.
-No.
It's a historical marker or site.
They won't ever be able to shut it down
like they wanted to.
This used to be,
like back in the day, where they did mine.
There actually used to be the mine
right here in the middle of the town.
-The mine was right here?
-Yeah, in the middle.
-See where this…
-It was historical.
People make a lot of money
working in Morenci for the mine.
Yeah, that's all they do.
I mean, I work at a restaurant,
but I don't make that much money.
But I should go up there to the mine work.
They're making a lot, huh?
There's more to life than money.
-Their rent is cheap up there too.
But see, if you lose your job or whatever,
you gotta find your own place.
'Cause if you lose your job
and you have a company home,
then you're kind of sh*t out of luck.
-You're out of town.
Most of the idiots will sit,
just live in those houses.
And then if they retire,
they don't have nowhere to live.
-Right, so once they retire,
they have to leave town.
Mm-hmm.
So my mom, she used to work
for the company up there in Morenci.
And she ended up getting breast cancer.
And she also messed up her back at work.
But she didn't report it right away,
so she fought for a lot of years
to try to get her disability.
And she wasn't able to get it
until she kept fighting for it.
But they made us move out of
the company housing and everything.
And we lived there for like 13 years
when we were kids.
[Peter] Okay, interesting.
So these towns, right next to one another,
have a totally different dynamic.
And what I learned in Baghdad,
there's randomized drug testing
with the mine.
So there's not much drug usage
with the adults.
And look at this.
I mean, what is that, 1913?
Not even that long ago
when you think about it, guys.
I mean, just one
extremely long lifetime ago,
this town was thriving.
I'm sure there were bar fights,
gun fights,
everything going on here.
We have the Morenci Miners Union.
United Steelworkers of America.
Clifton Social Club over here.
And some for sale buildings.
Not much of an economy here now, obviously.
And that's how it goes. The mines run out.
The people leave.
The town goes downhill.
Now because the mine's functioning up there
I think a lot of the miners
that work in Morenci live here.
I think that's the story.
Look at these classics.
Just a step back in time, you guys.
Okay, here we go, museum.
Alright guys, want to take a break
to talk to you about the Inner Circle.
That's the video platform
we have off of YouTube.
Behind the scenes,
deeper thoughts, and deeper dives
on some of these topics,
questions and answers.
Even occasional, very occasional.
I try to do it more.
But Natalia,
who's pretty much the brains
and foundation
of this whole operation.
-Doing the editing.
-Just behind the scenes editing.
Just yeah, but she comes out
for our Inner Circle.
Got a link down below you guys.
Would love you to be part of it.
It's a place where a lot of the topics
on these videos sort of fly by them.
But can give deeper thoughts,
deeper lessons learned.
Revelations.
It's a closer connection between
you, the audience,
and us.
Would love you to join.
Postcards, analog.
We got a lot of digital in our world.
There are three tiers down below.
And the third tier, fellow traveler,
we send you a postcard from every series.
I sign it at the bottom,
Natalia writes the address
and she feels great when she does it
'cause it's a connection
to you guys, the audience.
Without you,
we wouldn't be able to do this.
We'd love you to be
part of the Inner Circle.
Link down below.
And we have
a great holiday Christmas special.
-With a recap of the videos from this year.
-That's right.
With all the behind the scenes,
the aftermath.
I'm asking Peter questions.
I'm asking Natalia questions.
So, it's a really cool talk and also
we'll be posting another video
with questions and answers
that people will ask us
and we'll do a Q&A on the platform.
Yep. Love to see you guys there.
Now, back to the story.
-[woman] Hello.
-[Peter] Hello, ma'am. How are you?
-I'm good.
-All right.
-How are you?
-Good. Are you in charge here?
For today. [chuckles]
That's great. Well, I'm in luck then.
I just came from Morenci.
That's New Morenci.
-What do you mean, New Morenci?
Morenci has been moved
three times.
-Because of the mine?
-Mm-hmm.
So, when they keep expanding,
they just move the town?
-Mm-hmm.
-Oh, wow.
They build new houses for the workers.
I'll show you.
There's some pictures. Let me…
-Okay.
And so, what was it like growing up here?
Oh, I loved it. I didn't grow up here.
Let me show you.
'Cause the only way you
can explain this right here,
this town, the way it is here kinda,
is where I grew up.
These started in 1882.
-Mm-hmm.
-Okay.
This picture was taken
in 1982 or right after.
-Right around there? Okay.
The last building left
was the high school right here.
There actually was
four mining companies here.
-Okay. That was the town.
All these old buildings.
Yeah. See the houses down in here?
-Yeah.
-They were here.
There was towns everywhere.
They had a smelter up there.
They had, I think, four narrow-gauge
railroads going up and down
from Clifton to here and everywhere.
But see how this is,
see the houses are gone here.
Yeah.
Now, the people in Morenci,
Old Morenci, original,
they owned their home,
but they did not own the ground under it.
The companies did.
So, the companies
paid them for their homes and gave them…
-'Cause most of them worked for the mine.
-Okay.
And they gave them homes
in Stargo and Plantsite.
And part of Old Morenci
that weren't… like all these back here.
They moved them elsewhere
and these were left.
-Okay.
And then they moved them into
the homes that they built.
And then when they rebuilt the New Morenci,
the mine owns all the homes,
the company owns the homes.
-Up there.
-Yeah.
Now, not down here.
-Clifton, does the company
own any of the homes here?
They own part of the ground down here.
-That's 2010?
-Yeah.
So, I drove all the way up
through this thing.
Did you go up to the open pit look out?
Yeah, I did.
Okay. This is Morenci right here,
and then this is Clifton down here?
-Yeah.
The two towns are right next to each other.
Just a bit of a drop elevation-wise.
This is what used to be up there.
-Beautiful old buildings, huh?
-Yeah.
-State of the art.
West of St. Louis, they said.
-Oh, look at this.
-Now, this is when it's a little newer.
See, you went through that tunnel.
-Yeah, I did.
-This is before the tunnel.
This is an underground mine.
Can you imagine doing that by hand?
-So it was just like bucket by bucket?
-Yeah.
Now this is Clifton, the way it was.
-Your main street, I just walked down here.
-This is the main street.
Holler, or come and join,
one of the two.
[chuckles]
This is the same railroad bridge
you're using now.
-Okay.
-The highway's over on this side.
They've changed that bridge.
-So back in the day,
the air must have been really bad.
When you were a kid,
do you remember that?
When I was a kid growing up
in Old Morenci and Stargo,
they had these big windows
and they'd open the top window.
-Okay.
-That would be cool enough for us.
But the sulfur smoke would come
every morning, usually around 11:00.
The sulfur smoke?
-From the smelter that used to be there.
-Oh.
Was that really bad?
-The air quality?
-I don't know.
You were used to it.
How is it now?
You don't have a smelter anymore.
-Okay.
They took the smelter down.
-[Peter] What are these?
-[woman] Are you from here.
-[man] Phoenix now but I'm from here.
-[woman] You're from Phoenix?
I live there now, but I'm from Morenci.
-[Peter] Oh, cool.
-[woman] When did you leave?
I went to the service in '90
and then I got out, came back,
and then… pretty small town.
I took off to Phoenix
to find some more opportunities.
This is where Circle K is now.
-Oh, that's a little different.
-[laughs]
[man] They had a terminus
for the train right here.
[woman] A turnaround.
It was over more towards the store.
So, sir, you grew up here.
Then you moved out. Now you've come back.
What does it feel like now
when you come back?
It's an incredible amount of change.
I wish…
You know, I can see that it's encouraging
to see some revitalization of Chase Creek.
You know, they're trying,
but there's still a way to go.
I'd like to be able to see folks be able to
get involved, like with Bisbee and Jerome,
and try to really revitalize it.
I told a man from Tombstone one day
we had a chamber mixer here one time.
I told him. I said, you know what?
The only thing Tombstone and Bisbee
has over Greenlee County,
Clifton, and Morenci is the freeway.
People go down I-10, and they see
Tombstone, Bisbee, and off they go.
-So you guys want tourists here?
Yes!
-Okay.
-Well, here we go. I'm making a video.
-[laughs]
I'll get them here.
And they've gotten a few new
bed and breakfast and stuff here,
and they're hurting for housing.
You've got a county that is…
used to be known for cotton,
copper, or…
-Cattle.
-Cattle, cotton, and copper.
Yeah.
-What is this picture right here?
That's the Chinese store.
It used to be here on Chase Creek,
I think, or no, it was on Eastside.
I can't remember.
I'm not quite that old. [laughs]
This told the rules for the employees.
So the two languages here
were English and Chinese?
-And Spanish.
-And Spanish?
More Spanish than…
-Than Chinese.
And they did a lot of these rock walls.
The Mexican people and the Chinese.
The Chinese had a lot of businesses.
They knew how to run a business.
So that's how miners were paid.
They would use those books.
They'd get them out at the store.
They'd spend all their money
with these coupon books.
And then sometimes
they wouldn't get a paycheck
'cause they'd take it out
of their next paycheck.
It'd be like, you buy this from me
and you spend all the coupons in it,
as an example.
-You know?
-Okay, sure.
And then for two weeks,
you'd buy your groceries,
'cause the PD store had everything.
Furniture, sheets,
pillowcases, blankets,
everything you needed.
And you bought the coupons
and you could go shopping at the store.
You didn't actually buy them, they issued
them to you and they kept track.
Then by the time the two weeks is over
and the pay period is over,
you spent your whole paycheck.
Your wife has
or somebody has on the coupons.
So you owe your soul to the company store.
If you ever need more of those,
you just let me know.
-Here, you can have one.
-Thank you.
It's a lot of great history.
"Stories of Arizona's Mines
and Early Mineral Discoveries."
-[Peter] Fantastic.
-[woman] Jack did this?
When did he do this?
They're old.
[Peter] You have a virtual tour on YouTube,
correct?
Yeah. And the library,
the public library did that.
So if people want to know more
about this place, go to that video.
[man] There was a lot of stores
up and down here.
There was restaurants.
Too many bars, I guess, really.
There's about three or four bars, you know.
-Is it sad for you to see it so quiet now?
Or it's just the way life goes?
It's sad for people that left and come back
and they see it the way it is now.
Because I had a schoolmate come back.
We had a little girl's reunion
one time when we graduated in '61.
And two of them just cried.
They said, "I won't come back."
Because not only was
the town different, new town,
their house was gone.
The school was gone.
The stores were gone.
All those pictures I showed you in there,
they're gone.
And it was a culture shock
coming and seeing
than staying here and living with it.
You know what I'm saying? It's different.
-You saw it go gradually.
-Yeah.
-To some degree.
-It wasn't like a, ugh, like…
This is a newer business.
Look at that.
The People's Bank and Trust Co.
And yeah, they're trying.
It's got the bones for it.
-How you doing?
-Hi.
When did you start this?
We just opened Monday.
-Are you serious?
-Yeah.
-We're super into it.
-Okay.
We want to revitalize Chase Creek
and get it popping again.
It used to be like
a main commercial district
and I think it'd be fun
to get it going again.
So, one building at a time.
So, we bought this building
and gutted it and renovated it.
And upstairs, we have an Airbnb.
You got food products. You got shirts.
You got a little bit of everything.
Yep. A lot of it's local artisans
just supporting their crafts.
We have surprisingly talented people here.
-Are you from here?
-No, I'm from New Mexico.
And then I went up to Utah for college
and married a guy, whatever.
But we've been back…
We've been here for like eight years.
-How is it?
-I love it.
-You love it?
I didn't think I would. I was like,
I was dreading the small town stuff.
Thinking, oh my gosh, what are we doing?
But my sister had lived here
and we came and visited
the year before we moved actually
and thought
what a cute little charming town.
And then we ended up moving here,
which we didn't expect.
-That's so cool.
Do you notice a big difference
between here, Clifton, and Morenci?
Um, Morenci gets maintained more
'cause the mine has more money.
-Okay, so what do you think
of the company town concept?
I think it could be like
a corrupt sort of thing,
but I think it's actually run pretty well.
-Morenci?
-Mm-hmm.
-Yeah.
-I think it's charming.
We live in a Morenci house
in Clifton actually,
but they have like
one little section in Clifton
that's technically Morenci, but not.
-Okay, so the mine
owns the house that you live in.
Mm-hmm.
-You pay rent.
-Mm-hmm.
But cheap rent.
-It's very cheap, right?
-Mm-hmm.
Yeah, we were kind of nervous
'cause we wanted to buy
a beautiful big fancy house
and there just aren't here.
-Yeah.
But it's kind of nice 'cause then everyone
just sort of is on equal footing that way.
You feel like a camaraderie
sort of that way. I don't know.
Like we're in identical houses,
but you still have your individuality,
but then you're not
competing with the Joneses sort of
'cause just we all…
you can go on more vacations with your kids
because you're not paying it all in rent.
But I don't, I don't feel that competition,
especially after Utah,
which you do feel, you know?
Far outpost in the desert.
Old time feeling.
Slow pace of life.
Clifton Hotel and Bar.
The assessor's office is looking spiffy.
It's the fire department too.
That is beautiful.
Right up on the hillsides.
Cute little zones here.
Right into the cliffs.
San Francisco River flowing through town.
And here you go.
Some of those original mining homes.
I'm sure there's some
multi-generational homes.
Families that grew up here
and then their kids take it over
and their kids take it over.
I think there's gotta be some of that.
[Peter] Are you guys brothers?
-No, that's my son.
-Yeah, that's my dad.
-Oh, wow.
Yeah, thanks.
You just made his day, dude.
Okay. So the homes down here,
you guys are buying?
Yeah. All these are our owned.
-But you're working up at the mine?
-Yeah, yeah. We work up there.
-How things going these days?
-Good so far.
-I was born and raised here. So was he.
-No way.
I've been working for, what,
30 years now. So…
And copper's good right now, right?
Copper's good. Yeah, I can't complain.
It fluctuates. But yeah, it's been
the highest since I've been working, right?
-No way.
-Oh, yeah.
So do you know when copper's high,
you notice a difference with employment?
-There's more money floating around?
-Yeah.
So your life just completely revolves
around that one mineral.
-Pretty much, yeah.
-[laughter]
Yeah, that's about it.
Around here anyways, yeah.
-But there's…
-We have byproducts too,
but that's our main…
-But there's decades in that mine, right?
Oh, yeah, yeah.
I'm like, what, third or fourth generation
miner in my family.
-Oh, no way.
Yeah.
And then possibly my great-grandfather.
I'm not too sure. I can't remember.
-Okay, so it's in the blood.
-It's, yeah.
-Jacob. Nice to meet you.
-Peter.
-Yeah.
-Oh, that's cool.
-My son, Jacob Jr.
-Jacob Jr. Nice.
-Jacob Jr.
He actually works over at the mine
in Tucson in Sarita for Freeport.
-Yeah, Freeport's everywhere.
-Same company, just different area.
My daughter works…
She's in the mine, but she actually works
for a contractor, Napa.
-Okay.
-And then my other boy, he's the youngest.
He's actually a mechanic in the garage,
which I'm the supervisor at.
Freeport sent me out of the country,
so I've been to Indonesia.
-Yeah, so…
-How was that?
It was great. It was good down there.
It was nice. I liked it.
We all had an opportunity
to move down there, work there, but…
Yeah, my wife works for Freeport as well,
So we all… We're all working there.
-And then everyone knows everyone?
-Yeah, everybody here.
-So you don't worry about…
You're either family
or close friends, right?
Okay, so it's very hot here in the summer
obviously but you just rip up the mountain.
Yeah. Two hours, two and a half hours.
Two and a half hours.
You're at, like, 8,000, 9,000 feet?
Yup.
And then it's cool up there in the summers?
It's cool up there.
I think the highest it gets, maybe 80, 85.
85 is, like, really hot up there,
but most of the time
it's between 75 and 80.
-Cold nights?
Oh, nights are like,
yeah, get down to the 40s, 50s.
-Midsummer?
-Summer, yeah.
That's during the midsummer, you know.
Heater at nighttime, you know,
depending on how you are.
-In the summer in Arizona?
During the day, yeah, you turn on
the AC for a little while. [chuckles]
And then you come down here
and it's baking out.
Yeah, and then you head down the hill
and you're like, oh, man, this is terrible.
-But winters are nice here?
Yeah, winters are great here, yeah.
You say Morenci is a mining camp?
Yeah, that's what it's really considered.
-Because they move it around?
Because, yeah,
it's all owned by Freeport, the mine, yeah.
I talked to Tammy at the museum.
She said that.
Yeah, I was going to say,
if you hit them up…
-Tammy's great.
You guys have a lot of big pickup trucks.
-Yeah.
Is that where the money goes?
Pretty much, yeah.
Yeah, we got horses too,
so we got, you know.
-Horses here?
-Yeah, they're up at the corrals.
-Right up the road.
-You have corrals here?
Yeah, up on top, yeah.
And that's actually Freeport-owned,
so we rent them from Freeport.
I think we pay, like,
50 bucks a month for a nice little stable.
-Get his license plate right there.
-Yeah.
-[Peter] Life is good out here?
-Oh, yeah.
Cheap, easy.
Overtime.
-Overtime? Good overtime?
-Yeah.
There's a lot of money that could be made
if you really want it, you know.
It's hard to hire people from the outside.
-Why is that?
-'Cause they come in from a bigger city,
and they see this place and they're like,
"Oh, what's there to do around here?"
So, most of the time
they don't end up living here
or they stay here
for a few months and they're gone
'cause there's just not
too much to do around here, right?
Besides traveling three hours
to Phoenix or Tucson.
Yeah, but if you're into horses,
you're into your mountain cabin.
Yeah, if you're an outdoorsman,
this is perfect right here.
-Yeah.
-You know everyone in town.
-You got your buddies.
-Yeah.
Sounds pretty sweet.
During the week you're working, right?
So, there's, it's not like you're gonna
do something after work.
You're pretty much tired.
You want to come home,
eat, sleep, go back to work.
It's the weekends where you can go
spend your money outside of this place.
Yeah, and you're not spending much here?
Yeah, no. It's, like I said, it's…
-It's all about the truck.
-That's where you spend it.
-Yeah. [laughs]
[wind blowing]
Well, this is what the streets are like
here in Morenci, Saturday afternoon.
We were way up there in the mine
and it's just neighborhood
after neighborhood
looking like this.
These must be the one bedroom,
one bath, or studio options,
which I saw online are $200.
It's just this contained life.
That's what I'm feeling here in Morenci.
Well look, they got
all these little parks here.
Home of the Wildcats.
Welcome to the hill.
Okay, just got a tip from a guy
that didn't want to be on camera
saying that this part of town over here
is the nice part of town.
These are the managers
or the higher paid positions.
Their housing's a bit different.
It's almost like a separate zone
of Morenci, like an island.
Beautiful scenery here, though.
Look at this.
Lights starting to soften a little bit.
Desert colors come alive.
And here we go.
Yeah, feels different.
Got these beautiful cypress trees.
So this is wealthy Morenci.
Not too many homes out here.
A little more space between them.
A little bit bigger.
Nice park in the middle.
And I think that's it.
That's about it.
The Hollywood Hills of Morenci.
[children playing]
[man] My boy's right there.
The one looking this way.
-Is he pretty good?
-Oh yeah.
-So people mostly dig it out here, yeah?
Oh yeah.
And like there's
all different departments, right?
You got your dirt work.
You got your SX plant.
You got the mill. You got…
So it's like a different range of people.
Engineers.
There's people from all over the world.
-What you guys got going here
is unbelievable.
I work for a company called Swap
Constructions. A contractor.
-Okay.
And I run heavy equipment for them.
-Right on.
-So you don't work for Freeport?
-No.
I'm contracted out for them.
-Contracted out for them.
-So there's a lot of that going on?
-Oh yeah.
-That's fun.
-It's fun?
The dirt work part's fun.
-It's like being a kid and playing around?
-Oh yeah. Big sandbox.
-You started at 16?
-Yeah. As a laborer.
What's it go up to?
I'm up to 35 right now.
-Nice.
-And I still have room to climb.
Like we were working on
this pipe corridor
and if you look over the edge
from off the high wall.
It's like 4,000 foot to the bottom
to the pond down below you.
Long ways.
-So high risk?
-Yeah.
Yeah. No room for human error.
There's randomized drug testing, right?
Oh yeah. Well yeah.
I just got random a couple months ago.
Okay. So no adults are really using drugs
unless they want to get kicked out of town.
Yeah. Exactly.
That's what happens?
Oh yeah.
You get blackballed for seven years.
Okay.
And that's off of every
Freeport-McMoRan site.
That's Chino, Bagdad.
So if you piss dirty here, then you can't
go work at none of them places either.
And that even detects weed?
Yep.
-So no weed, nothing?
-Nope.
And nobody plays with that 'cause
their whole life gets thrown upside down.
It would suck if you put…
Like I got 11 years up here.
Almost 11. March will be 11 years.
Okay.
It'd just be ruined.
It'd just be a waste of 11 years.
You'd be kicked out of your house.
No health insurance. No job.
Nothing.
-Your wife would hate you.
-I'll guarantee it. [laughs]
So only a couple of
restaurants open tonight.
Miner's Diner and Bar.
This is what it's gonna be.
Are these guys good chefs back there?
Yeah, that one's the best one right there.
Best chef in Morenci?
Yeah. Best chef in Morenci. [giggles]
-All right. All right.
Mexican options.
Enchiladas you said?
-Those are excellent.
-Mm-hmm.
-Chicken.
-Chicken?
-Yes.
-Perfect.
-Can I get your name, please?
-Peter.
Are you from Morenci?
I am. I'm in high school.
-How's the high school?
It's good. It's really good.
The school district is good.
We do pretty good, academic-wise.
-Oh, you do well?
-Yes.
Oh, that's cool. Nice.
Alright, great. Thank you.
Of course. Is there anything I can get you?
salsa, sour cream, or anything?
-I'll take a salsa. Thank you.
-Perfect.
Mm-hmm.
Basic.
Straightforward.
Morenci style.
Good beans.
Tender chicken.
Mm-hmm.
Hits the spot.
For sure after today.
That was a long one.
Started in Silver City, New Mexico.
A couple hours from here.
Beautiful, beautiful countryside.
This part of the country
is quite special for sure.
Interesting place.
Interesting way of living.
The company town
holds strong here in 2025.
Morenci, Arizona.
I'd say at least 99% of Americans
wouldn't even think
a company town still existed.
But it does.
Also have another company town video
somewhere around here.
It's called Bagdad without an H.
Bagdad, Arizona.
Thanks for coming along
on that journey, you guys.
Until the next one.
[Western music]